<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/writing</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/writing"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The Physics of Culture</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/the-physics-of-culture/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/the-physics-of-culture/</id>
    <published>2019-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-21T16:00:42+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Architecture has reignited my curiosity for a more mature web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate enough to attend the annual Peter Rice Lecture for the second year in a row this week and left the lecture hall in awe about the work and principles shared by Yvonne Farrell and Shelley McNamara from Grafton Architects in their lecture titled "The Physics of Culture".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention Shelly even though she didn't speak because one of the core values of Grafton Architects is promoting that "architecture is collaborative". The same is true—or at least should be—for a design practise but maybe we don't instil that enough in our beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;architecture impacts on all of us (so does design)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;light affects structure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the union between the material and the spiritual world as a way to describe the beautiful cathedral in Majorca&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking about a building as a "machine that holds light"&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The skin of cities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"The structure is immense but it embraces you"&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Architecture is "a silent language that speaks"&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"Art, history, politics, poetry, against hard data" van humbolt?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buildings—"the built enclosure of people's lives"&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking about how the air of a city moves through a building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter Rice — committed to collaboration across disciplines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"The earth is our client"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Underland</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/underland/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/underland/</id>
    <published>2019-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:53:51+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Robert Macfarlane's &lt;em&gt;Underland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; is already one of my favourite reads of the year and I'm only about a third of the way through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He speaks about his experiences with such romanticism and I've been adoring the references throughout. The same was true for &lt;em&gt;The Old Ways&lt;/em&gt;, which I read earlier this year. Here's one of my favourite passages—and an quote from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_de_Bernières"&gt;Louis de Bernières&lt;/a&gt;—for your enjoyment and my future reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lying there among the trees, despite a learned wariness towards anthropomorphism, I find it hard not to imagine these aboreal relations in terms of tenderness, generosity and even love: the respectful distance of their shy crowns, the kissing branches that have pleached with one another, the unseen connections forged by root and hyphae between seemingly distant trees. I remember something Louis de Bernières has written about a relationship that endured into the old age: 'we had roots that grew towards each other underground, and when all the pretty blossom had fallen from our branches we found that we were one tree and not two.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small class="db mt4 gray"&gt;1. Robert Macfarlane, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/41817481-underland?from_search=true&amp;amp;qid=fACBglecTz&amp;amp;rank=1" target="_blank"&gt;Underland ↗&lt;/a&gt;, Hamish Hamilton, 2019&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For Ursula Le Guin</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/for-ursula/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/for-ursula/</id>
    <published>2018-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:31:21+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/writing/le-guin/ursula-le-guin.jpg" alt="Source: " /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Photo by Jill Krementz, All Rights Reserved&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great privilege to have my first experience of Ursula Le Guin's writing back in 2015. Late to the party, you could say, but I'm glad I arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up a copy of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13642.A_Wizard_of_Earthsea?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true"&gt;A Wizard of Earthsea&lt;/a&gt; — the first book in her Earthsea series — in Powell's Books, Portland OR. and devoured it. It wasn't until her passing this week that I learned that Ursula spent most of her life in Portland, a nice coincidence that I happened upon her work in that city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been dipping in and out of her work ever since, continuing with the Earthsea books and some of her other works. I'm currently reading her translated version of Lao Tzu's "Tao Te Ching". I'm a big fan of her work and I'm glad there's so much left for me to read. It's sad in a way that death can jolt one into a period of obsession over another's work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many wonderful things about Le Guin have come to light over the past few days, things that have always been but a lot of us are only now seeing as her "legacy", of what she left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to share a few things I've stumbled upon the past few days because they've brought me joy. And, of course, if you haven't already you must add Ursula's &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/874602.Ursula_K_Le_Guin?from_search=true"&gt;cannon of work&lt;/a&gt; to your reading list for the year, as I will be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2018/jan/24/ursula-k-le-guin-margaret-atwood-tribute"&gt;Ursula K Le Guin, by Margaret Atwood: ‘One of the literary greats of the 20th century’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/24/books/review/for-ursula-le-guin-poem-naomi-novik.html"&gt;For Ursula (a poem by Naomi Novik)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/booksblog/2018/jan/24/essential-novels-ursula-k-le-guin"&gt;Don't know where to start? The essential novels of Ursula K Le Guin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KarenAbbott/status/955946917862703104"&gt;"Gentlemen, I just don't belong here."&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://literary-arts.org/archive/ursula-le-guin-margaret-atwood-rebroadcast/"&gt;Ursula Le Guin &amp;amp; Margaret Atwood discuss writing (audio)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People who deny the existence of dragons are often eaten by dragons. From within.” — Ursula Le Guin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lessons from a Year of Freelance</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/lessons-from-freelance/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/lessons-from-freelance/</id>
    <published>2018-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:31:24+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of last year I found myself overwhelmed with anxiety and, to be quite honest, dejection about the type of work I was doing. I knew I needed a change so I decided to quit my job with no real plan for what was to come next. A little preparation with finances to give myself a bit of a runway and I was ready to greet the world of freelance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in a similar position hopefully you can find something useful in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community"&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people around me were the driving force behind all the work I got this year. Some of these people I've know for a long time, some were new friends that I made through attending events, being active on Twitter, joining new Slack communities, and working on small side-projects. I can't stress how important it is to get out there and make acquaintances/friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I've found is people will pass on work to those they trust when they're too busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"I'm booked up for the next two months but I know someone who can help!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advice here is &lt;strong&gt;get to know your community&lt;/strong&gt;. If your thinking about going freelance in the future it's important to be proactive about this. Also, make sure you deliver good work. If someone recommends you their reputation is on the line as well as yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="money"&gt;Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn't expect this year was to earn more money working independently than I did in full-time employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is important to any small business. Keeping your finances in check and planning accordingly is vital to keeping your books  balanced. It's also important to expense as much as you can against your taxes—a good accountant can help with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of great software to help with finances and scheduling as a freelancer. &lt;a href="http://fre.ag/46dvp0jl"&gt;FreeAgent&lt;/a&gt; is wonderful for keeping track of invoices, expenses, and taxes (you can even pay your taxes directly in FreeAgent), &lt;a href="https://cushionapp.com/"&gt;Cushion&lt;/a&gt; for planning out your projects and making sure you have work lined up, &lt;a href="https://www.getharvest.com/"&gt;Harvest&lt;/a&gt; for time-tracking. They all integrate nicely with each other too, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/writing/freelance/cushionapp.png" alt="Cushion" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as contracts go, I prefer signing long-term ones. Everyone is different but I found this the best way to really get involved with a team/project. 4 month contracts suited me pretty well and if you're interested in what my contract looks like you can &lt;a href="/uploads/contract"&gt;find it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;don't undervalue yourself&lt;/strong&gt; and make sure you get paid on time. Your clients need to understand this from the get go, adding late fees to your contract is a good way to make sure you get paid punctually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="things-go-wrong"&gt;Things Go Wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes things don't go the way you want them to. I've been fortunate enough to avoid this for the most part but two pieces of invaluable advice I got early on was; it's OK to say no and also to walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made sure the latter was in my contract and the former was something I learned over time about the type of work I wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"If either party wish to terminate the contract, a grace period of 14 days must be given."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would say here is, make sure your business account is healthy before your personal account. Early on, maybe pay yourself a small salary and save any additional money you get so you have some security if things do go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="some-rules"&gt;Some Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have mentioned these in passing but I wanted to highlight a few extra rules to close:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It's OK to say no&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeping your clients happy will lead to more work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything you do online is part of your brand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep active; write, build, and share your work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You're a one person show now; learn about sales, marketing, content strategy, communication, and scheduling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don't get discouraged, the work will come&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on side-projects in your downtime, this can lead to the type of work you want&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I'm sorry: but maybe that LinkedIn account &lt;strong&gt;is a good idea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expect the feeling of risk to never go away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Screen Sabbatical</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/screen-sabbatical/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/screen-sabbatical/</id>
    <published>2016-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:31:27+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I took a short trip to Co. Donegal this past week to recharge after a busy few months. I planned this trip to get away from my computer, to relax and read, to walk around the Donegal countryside without thinking about work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Thursday when I arrived I largely did what I planned to. I read Carl Sagan’s ‘Cosmos’ all day and through his charasmetic words was transported through the Universe. My phone was on 5% from the day’s journey and I found myself checking it once or twice in the evening to see if anyone had tried to contact me. When I looked at the screen I was greeted by a list of notifications; Kickstarter emails, Quora answers, Reminders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set my phone down that night and let it die. The next day—16th December—I didn’t look at a single screen. Not a phone, or a television, or a Kindle. It was strange, I tried to recall the last time I went through a full day screenless. Our lives are built around screens, it was impossible to place, likely sometime in the mid 90s but I really can’t remember. When did you last go a full day without looking at a screen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked, I read, I wrote (this in my notebook, in the evening). I found a sense of comfort in the glow of the fire and the singing of the kettle. It was a welcome change from the brightness of a screen and the sometimes anxiety inducing buzz of a phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I do love technology, but I need more of these “screen sabbaticals”, I implore you to give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
