<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/writing</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/writing"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2020-05-08T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital Design Is Place Building</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/digital-design-is-place-building/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/digital-design-is-place-building/</id>
    <published>2020-05-08T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2020-05-08T12:59:29+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Test&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Events In 2020</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/events-2020/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/events-2020/</id>
    <published>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-05T12:40:37+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's that time of the year where the last event ends and I start thinking about what I want to attend the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very fortunate to attend some incredible design, art, and music events in 2019; XOXO, Uenoland, Other Voices, and more. I'm starting to think about what I'd like to attend next year, so I figured I'd share it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-adventures"&gt;New Adventures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fifth edition of the wonderful New Adventures; a conference exploring speculative and critical design, radical inclusivity, climate, sustainability, and much more. It's been years since I attended New Adventures and I'm looking forward to making the journey to Nottingham in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://newadventuresconf.com/2020/"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="uenoland"&gt;Uenoland&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inaugural Uenoland was a lot of fun, I met some incredible people and really enjoyed the creative nature of the talks. The second edition of Uenoland will be in the autumn of 2020 in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ueno.land/"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="do-lectures"&gt;Do Lectures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've wanted to attend Do Lectures for many years and I think it's finally time. Talks center around the themes of business, creativity, environment, social change, and wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thedolectures.com/"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="xoxo"&gt;XOXO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XOXO holds a special place in my heart, a fantastic event full of wonderful people. The festival is held every September in beautiful Portland, Oregon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxofest.com/"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="u"&gt;99U&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never attended 99U but it's been on my radar for the past couple of years. This year's theme of 'The Creative Self' has peaked my interest and I hope to attend it in June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://conference.99u.com/#overview"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="other-voices"&gt;Other Voices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having just come back from my first ever Other Voices in the far west of Ireland, I'm already planning my return. A very special event centered around music, with talks (&lt;a href="https://www.irelandsedge.net/"&gt;Ireland's Edge ↗&lt;/a&gt;) on sustainability, the arts, technology, innovation, storytelling and human experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.othervoices.ie/content/other-voices-2019"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="likeminds"&gt;Likeminds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something a little different, Likeminds brings together artists, designers, writers, technologists, scientists, and others to address a single theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.likeminds.camp/"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="material"&gt;Material&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Material is another conference that I've wanted to attend for the past couple of years. It has an interesting tagline that I'm curious to explore: "a conference exploring the concept of the Web as a material".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://material.is/2020/"&gt;Visit Website ↗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Downtown Is For People</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/downtown-is-for-people/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/downtown-is-for-people/</id>
    <published>2019-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-25T10:27:33+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an excerpt from The Exploding Metropolis&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;—a piece of text that examines urban decline and suburban sprawl, transportation, city politics, open space, and the character and fabric of cities. This excerpt was written by Jane Jacobs, the great author and urbanist who wrote The Death and Life of Great American Cities&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and The Economy of Cities&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, both of which I highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a critical time for the future of the city. All over the country civic leaders and planners are preparing a series of redeveloped projects that will set the character of the centre of our cities for generations to come. Great tracts, many blocks wide, are being razed; only a few cities have their new downtown projects already under construction; but almost every big city is getting ready to build, and the plans will soon be set.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What will the projects look like? They will be spacious, parklike, and uncrowded. They will feature long green vistas. They will be stable and symmetrical and orderly. They will be clean, impressive, and monumental They will have all the attributes or a well-kept, dignified cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;And each project will look very much like the next one: the Golden Gateway office and apartment centre planned for San Francisco;  the Civic Center for New Orleans; the Lower Hill auditorium and apartment project for Pittsburgh; the Convention Center for Cleveland; the Quality Hill offices and apartments for Kansas City; the Capitol Hill project for Nashville.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;From city to city the architects' sketches conjure up the same dreary scene; here is no hint of individuality or whim or surprise, no hint that here is a city with a tradition and flavour all its own.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;These projects will not revitalise downtown; they will deaden it. For they work at cross-purposes to the city. They banish its variety.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is the premise of the critique that the best way to plan for downtown is to see how people use it today; to look for its strengths and to exploit and reinforce them. There is no logic that can be superimposed on the city; people make it, and it is to them, not buildings, they we must fit our plans. This does not mean accepting the present; downtown does need and overhaul, it is dirty, it is congested. But there are things that are right about it too, and by simple old-fashioned observation we can see what they are. We can see what people like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You're reading this piece of text on a design blog because when I read it I relate it to how stagnant the web has become is many ways. "Each project will look very like the next one" reminds my of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jongold/status/694591217523363840?s=20"&gt;this tweet by Jon Gold&lt;/a&gt;. This note is part of a larger essay I'm working on about the state of design at the end of this decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design on the web has changed a lot over the past 10 years, we really need to start observing where we've come from and where we are today so that we can start driving web design towards being a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;more mature discipline&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="gray f6 lh-copy ml0"&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Various Authors, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/552478.The_Exploding_Metropolis?from_search=true&amp;amp;qid=qbNpXCcnlM&amp;amp;rank=1" target="_blank"&gt;The Exploding Metropolis &amp;#8599;&lt;/a&gt;, University of California Press, 1993 (fp. 1958)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jane Jacobs, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/30833.The_Death_and_Life_of_Great_American_Cities?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true&amp;amp;qid=EEaIaYAN2D&amp;amp;rank=4" target="_blank"&gt;The Death and Life of Great American Cities &amp;#8599;&lt;/a&gt;, Random House, 2002 (fp. 1961)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jane Jacobs, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85398.The_Economy_of_Cities?from_search=true&amp;amp;qid=oiNlrfKBPV&amp;amp;rank=10" target="_blank"&gt;The Economy of Cities &amp;#8599;&lt;/a&gt;, Vintage, 1970  (fp. 1969)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Underland</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/underland/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/underland/</id>
    <published>2019-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:53:51+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Robert Macfarlane's &lt;em&gt;Underland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; is already one of my favourite reads of the year and I'm only about a third of the way through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He speaks about his experiences with such romanticism and I've been adoring the references throughout. The same was true for &lt;em&gt;The Old Ways&lt;/em&gt;, which I read earlier this year. Here's one of my favourite passages—and an quote from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_de_Bernières"&gt;Louis de Bernières&lt;/a&gt;—for your enjoyment and my future reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lying there among the trees, despite a learned wariness towards anthropomorphism, I find it hard not to imagine these aboreal relations in terms of tenderness, generosity and even love: the respectful distance of their shy crowns, the kissing branches that have pleached with one another, the unseen connections forged by root and hyphae between seemingly distant trees. I remember something Louis de Bernières has written about a relationship that endured into the old age: 'we had roots that grew towards each other underground, and when all the pretty blossom had fallen from our branches we found that we were one tree and not two.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small class="db mt4 gray"&gt;1. Robert Macfarlane, &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/41817481-underland?from_search=true&amp;amp;qid=fACBglecTz&amp;amp;rank=1" target="_blank"&gt;Underland ↗&lt;/a&gt;, Hamish Hamilton, 2019&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For Ursula Le Guin</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/for-ursula/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/for-ursula/</id>
    <published>2018-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:31:21+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/writing/le-guin/ursula-le-guin.jpg" alt="Source: " /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Photo by Jill Krementz, All Rights Reserved&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great privilege to have my first experience of Ursula Le Guin's writing back in 2015. Late to the party, you could say, but I'm glad I arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up a copy of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13642.A_Wizard_of_Earthsea?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true"&gt;A Wizard of Earthsea&lt;/a&gt; — the first book in her Earthsea series — in Powell's Books, Portland OR. and devoured it. It wasn't until her passing this week that I learned that Ursula spent most of her life in Portland, a nice coincidence that I happened upon her work in that city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been dipping in and out of her work ever since, continuing with the Earthsea books and some of her other works. I'm currently reading her translated version of Lao Tzu's "Tao Te Ching". I'm a big fan of her work and I'm glad there's so much left for me to read. It's sad in a way that death can jolt one into a period of obsession over another's work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many wonderful things about Le Guin have come to light over the past few days, things that have always been but a lot of us are only now seeing as her "legacy", of what she left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to share a few things I've stumbled upon the past few days because they've brought me joy. And, of course, if you haven't already you must add Ursula's &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/874602.Ursula_K_Le_Guin?from_search=true"&gt;cannon of work&lt;/a&gt; to your reading list for the year, as I will be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2018/jan/24/ursula-k-le-guin-margaret-atwood-tribute"&gt;Ursula K Le Guin, by Margaret Atwood: ‘One of the literary greats of the 20th century’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/24/books/review/for-ursula-le-guin-poem-naomi-novik.html"&gt;For Ursula (a poem by Naomi Novik)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/booksblog/2018/jan/24/essential-novels-ursula-k-le-guin"&gt;Don't know where to start? The essential novels of Ursula K Le Guin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KarenAbbott/status/955946917862703104"&gt;"Gentlemen, I just don't belong here."&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://literary-arts.org/archive/ursula-le-guin-margaret-atwood-rebroadcast/"&gt;Ursula Le Guin &amp;amp; Margaret Atwood discuss writing (audio)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People who deny the existence of dragons are often eaten by dragons. From within.” — Ursula Le Guin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lessons from a Year of Freelance</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writing/lessons-from-freelance/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writing/lessons-from-freelance/</id>
    <published>2018-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T21:31:24+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of last year I found myself overwhelmed with anxiety and, to be quite honest, dejection about the type of work I was doing. I knew I needed a change so I decided to quit my job with no real plan for what was to come next. A little preparation with finances to give myself a bit of a runway and I was ready to greet the world of freelance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in a similar position hopefully you can find something useful in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="community"&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people around me were the driving force behind all the work I got this year. Some of these people I've know for a long time, some were new friends that I made through attending events, being active on Twitter, joining new Slack communities, and working on small side-projects. I can't stress how important it is to get out there and make acquaintances/friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I've found is people will pass on work to those they trust when they're too busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"I'm booked up for the next two months but I know someone who can help!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advice here is &lt;strong&gt;get to know your community&lt;/strong&gt;. If your thinking about going freelance in the future it's important to be proactive about this. Also, make sure you deliver good work. If someone recommends you their reputation is on the line as well as yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="money"&gt;Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn't expect this year was to earn more money working independently than I did in full-time employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is important to any small business. Keeping your finances in check and planning accordingly is vital to keeping your books  balanced. It's also important to expense as much as you can against your taxes—a good accountant can help with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of great software to help with finances and scheduling as a freelancer. &lt;a href="http://fre.ag/46dvp0jl"&gt;FreeAgent&lt;/a&gt; is wonderful for keeping track of invoices, expenses, and taxes (you can even pay your taxes directly in FreeAgent), &lt;a href="https://cushionapp.com/"&gt;Cushion&lt;/a&gt; for planning out your projects and making sure you have work lined up, &lt;a href="https://www.getharvest.com/"&gt;Harvest&lt;/a&gt; for time-tracking. They all integrate nicely with each other too, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/writing/freelance/cushionapp.png" alt="Cushion" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as contracts go, I prefer signing long-term ones. Everyone is different but I found this the best way to really get involved with a team/project. 4 month contracts suited me pretty well and if you're interested in what my contract looks like you can &lt;a href="/uploads/contract"&gt;find it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;don't undervalue yourself&lt;/strong&gt; and make sure you get paid on time. Your clients need to understand this from the get go, adding late fees to your contract is a good way to make sure you get paid punctually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="things-go-wrong"&gt;Things Go Wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes things don't go the way you want them to. I've been fortunate enough to avoid this for the most part but two pieces of invaluable advice I got early on was; it's OK to say no and also to walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made sure the latter was in my contract and the former was something I learned over time about the type of work I wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"If either party wish to terminate the contract, a grace period of 14 days must be given."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would say here is, make sure your business account is healthy before your personal account. Early on, maybe pay yourself a small salary and save any additional money you get so you have some security if things do go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="some-rules"&gt;Some Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have mentioned these in passing but I wanted to highlight a few extra rules to close:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It's OK to say no&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeping your clients happy will lead to more work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything you do online is part of your brand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep active; write, build, and share your work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You're a one person show now; learn about sales, marketing, content strategy, communication, and scheduling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don't get discouraged, the work will come&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on side-projects in your downtime, this can lead to the type of work you want&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I'm sorry: but maybe that LinkedIn account &lt;strong&gt;is a good idea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expect the feeling of risk to never go away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
